<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<cpp:cpp xmlns:cpp="https://eden-fidelis.eu/cpp/cpp/"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xsi:schemaLocation="https://eden-fidelis.eu/cpp/cpp/ ../cpp.xsd"
    ID="CPP-017" xml:lang="en">
    <cpp:header>
        <cpp:label>Disposal</cpp:label>
        <cpp:authors>
            <cpp:author>Mikko Laukkanen</cpp:author>
            <cpp:author>Juha Lehtonen</cpp:author>
        </cpp:authors>
        <cpp:contributors>
            <cpp:contributor>Kris Dekeyser</cpp:contributor>
            <cpp:contributor>Johan Kylander</cpp:contributor>
        </cpp:contributors>
        <cpp:evaluators>
            <cpp:evaluator>Matthew Addis</cpp:evaluator>
            <cpp:evaluator>Felix Burger</cpp:evaluator>
            <cpp:evaluator>Maria Benauer</cpp:evaluator>
        </cpp:evaluators>
        <cpp:history>
            <cpp:version>
                <cpp:versionNumber>
                    <cpp:majorVersion>1</cpp:majorVersion>
                    <cpp:minorVersion>0</cpp:minorVersion>
                    <cpp:patchVersion>0</cpp:patchVersion>
                </cpp:versionNumber>
                <cpp:versionDate>2025-08-29</cpp:versionDate>
                <cpp:versionNotes>Milestone version</cpp:versionNotes>
            </cpp:version>
            <cpp:version>
                <cpp:versionNumber>
                    <cpp:majorVersion>1</cpp:majorVersion>
                    <cpp:minorVersion>1</cpp:minorVersion>
                    <cpp:patchVersion>0</cpp:patchVersion>
                </cpp:versionNumber>
                <cpp:versionDate>2026-03-27</cpp:versionDate>
                <cpp:versionNotes>Migration to XML</cpp:versionNotes>
            </cpp:version>
        </cpp:history>
    </cpp:header>
    <cpp:shortDefinition>
        The TDA enables the managed disposal of Information Packages and permits the retention
        and maintenance of Metadata even when the content of the Information Package has been
        removed from the TDA.
    </cpp:shortDefinition>
    <cpp:classification>
        <cpp:oaisClassification>Administration</cpp:oaisClassification>
        <cpp:logicalClassification>Lifecycle Management</cpp:logicalClassification>
    </cpp:classification>
    <cpp:descriptionAndScope>
        <p>
            Disposal refers to the process of removing or decommissioning <em>Information objects</em> from a
            TDA when its preservation is no longer needed or possible, or the <em>Object</em> has fulfilled its
            short-term preservation requirements. The latter requires appraisal and scheduling, where
            institutions establish clear policies defining how long different types of <em>Objects</em> should 
            be preserved. Disposal is usually triggered on <em>AIP</em> level.
        </p>
        <p>
            Disposal can be triggered by the following reasons:            
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>
                The TDA no longer has a legal basis to retain data (e.g. there is no consent);
            </li>
            <li>
                The TDA has been requested to remove data (e.g. there is a legitimate take down request);
            </li>        
            <li>
                The TDA has transferred data to another TDA and no longer needs to retain the data;
            </li>
            <li>
                The data is no longer usable by the designated community (e.g. because it has been
                corrupted or damaged and is beyond repair, or because quality assessment shows
                that it is no longer usable);
            </li>       
            <li>
                The data is no longer being used by the designated community, there is no
                expectation of future use, and organisation policy requires it to be disposed of (e.g. to
                reduce operational costs);
            </li>
            <li>
                The retention period for data has expired and the data should be disposed of (e.g. to
                ensure regulatory or legislative compliance);
            </li>
            <li>
                The TDA has alternative versions of the data that allow the original to be disposed of
                (e.g. as a result of normalisation or migration, or because a depositor has provided a
                superior version);
            </li>
            <li>
                The funding bodies that support the TDA no longer require or fund retention of the
                data (e.g. because the data no longer has funding body requirements for it to be
                accessible);
            </li>
            <li>
                The TDA elects to dispose of data (e.g. to help ensure its long-term sustainability in
                economic or ecological terms).
            </li>
        </ul>
        <p>
            The TDA must have a disposal policy, that in addition to the disposal of <em>Objects</em> or
            (derivative) <em>Files</em> includes related <em>Technical</em> and <em>Descriptive metadata</em>. 
            This is especially important when the related <em>Metadata</em> contains sensitive or 
            confidential information. The policy may state that all or most of the <em>Metadata</em> is 
            retained, disposed, or something in between. However, at minimum, TDA must create and retain 
            provenance <em>Metadata</em> about the disposal and provide (e.g. some “tombstone metadata” 
            for keeping the PIDs resolvable).
        </p>
        <p>
            The TDA must also consider the technical aspects of disposal, such as secure deletion
            methods that prevent data recovery, and the potential impact on related <em>Objects</em> that 
            may reference the disposed items.
        </p>
        <p>
            As the <em>Objects</em> can be copied and distributed across multiple storage systems and different
            storage media within a TDA, the complete physical removal of all copies might be complex
            and needs a timeframe. For instance, whereas a <em>File</em> is quick and easy to remove from a
            hard drive, it may be practically impossible to remove it from a magnetic tape. Thus, the
            actual disposal of copies of <em>Files</em> on tapes may occur only at the time when the tape is
            refreshed (i.e. the disposed <em>File</em> is then not included on the new tape). Therefore, the 
            first step to do could be a “logical disposal” (i.e. preventing access to the <em>Object</em>, 
            which gives time for the TDA to dispose of the physical copies). Sometimes this is referred to as
            “Deaccessioning” where <em>Objects</em> are removed from the collections that an organisation holds
            before the <em>Objects</em> are physically disposed of. The storage management information must be
            updated accordingly.
        </p>
        <p>
            Disposal decisions must be made carefully, as recovering disposed <em>Objects</em> may be
            impossible after physical deletion has been performed. Thus, effective disposal requires
            clear policies, robust documentation, secure technical procedures, and ongoing monitoring.
            The disposal process must produce audit trails and other relevant documentation about the
            disposal. An organisation may choose to implement additional safeguards as part of the
            disposal process depending on the type of data they hold. For example, data may be moved
            to a ‘trash bin’ for a period of time before permanent deletion takes place, which can be used
            to provide a short-term recovery window to guard against unwanted deletion (accidental or
            deliberate). Request, review or approval processes may also be employed. For example to
            prevent permanent deletion of an <em>Object</em> without explicit and documented approval from a
            requisite number of staff members who are authorised to approve disposal.
        </p>
    </cpp:descriptionAndScope>
    <cpp:process>
        <cpp:inputs>
            <cpp:data>
                <cpp:dataElement>Information objects</cpp:dataElement>
            </cpp:data>
            <cpp:metadata>
                <cpp:metadataElement>Rights metadata</cpp:metadataElement>
                <cpp:metadataElement>Technical metadata</cpp:metadataElement>
                <cpp:metadataElement>Descriptive metadata</cpp:metadataElement>
            </cpp:metadata>
            <cpp:guidance>
                <cpp:guidanceElement>Appraisal reports</cpp:guidanceElement>
                <cpp:guidanceElement>Quality reports</cpp:guidanceElement>
                <cpp:guidanceElement>Retention Policy</cpp:guidanceElement>
                <cpp:guidanceElement>Policies</cpp:guidanceElement>
                <cpp:guidanceElement>Legal aspects (e.g. licenses)</cpp:guidanceElement>
            </cpp:guidance>
        </cpp:inputs>
        <cpp:outputs>
            <cpp:metadata>
                <cpp:metadataElement>Provenance metadata</cpp:metadataElement>
                <cpp:metadataElement>Tombstone metadata</cpp:metadataElement>
            </cpp:metadata>
            <cpp:guidance>
                <cpp:guidanceElement>Audit trails</cpp:guidanceElement>
                <cpp:guidanceElement>
                    Possible certificates/records of disposal (especially in the case of sensitive or
                    confidential data)
                </cpp:guidanceElement>
            </cpp:guidance>
        </cpp:outputs>
        <cpp:triggerEvents>
            <cpp:triggerEvent>
                <cpp:description>
                    <span>
                        <em>Information packages</em> or <em>Files</em> are identified as corrupted and not
                        recoverable. Data corruption management may trigger the disposal. 
                    </span>
                </cpp:description>
                <cpp:correspondingCPP>CPP-004</cpp:correspondingCPP>
            </cpp:triggerEvent>
            <cpp:triggerEvent>
                <cpp:description>
                    <span>
                        Changes to community needs  
                    </span>
                </cpp:description>
                <cpp:correspondingCPP>CPP-018</cpp:correspondingCPP>
            </cpp:triggerEvent>
            <cpp:triggerEvent>
                <cpp:description>
                    <span>
                        The data quality assessment tasks may discover intolerably low-quality issues 
                        in a digital <em>Object</em> and provide a trigger for disposal
                    </span>
                </cpp:description>
                <cpp:correspondingCPP>CPP-019</cpp:correspondingCPP>
            </cpp:triggerEvent>
            <cpp:triggerEvent>
                <cpp:description>
                    <span>
                        Changes in legislature, rights, regulations, licenses, standards and alike  
                    </span>
                </cpp:description>
                <cpp:correspondingCPP>CPP-020</cpp:correspondingCPP>
            </cpp:triggerEvent>
            <cpp:triggerEvent>
                <cpp:description>
                    <span>
                        Detected risks   
                    </span>
                </cpp:description>
                <cpp:correspondingCPP>CPP-023</cpp:correspondingCPP>
            </cpp:triggerEvent>
            <cpp:triggerEvent>
                <cpp:description>
                    <span>
                        The file repair process may end up with a situation where the <em>File</em>
                        cannot be repaired. In such cases, disposal is required by the file
                        repair process.   
                    </span>
                </cpp:description>
                <cpp:correspondingCPP>CPP-027</cpp:correspondingCPP>
            </cpp:triggerEvent>            
        </cpp:triggerEvents>
        <cpp:stepByStepDescription>
            <cpp:stepGroup type="sequence">
                <cpp:stepGroup type="alternative" label="Alternative triggers">
            <cpp:step stepNumber="1a">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Quality reports 
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                    <cpp:supplier>CPP-004</cpp:supplier>
                    <cpp:supplier>CPP-027</cpp:supplier>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        TDA finds out, from management events or other triggering events,
                        that an <em>AIP</em> or <em>File</em> is corrupted and is not recoverable. The TDA
                        decides to dispose of it.
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            Storage management information (list of affected <em>AIPs</em>, <em>Files</em>)
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal request
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="1b">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Changes to the needs of the designated community
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                    <cpp:supplier>CPP-018</cpp:supplier>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        The designated community no longer has a need for the data, it is
                        demonstrably not making any use of the data, and there is no expectation 
                        that it will make any future use of the data. Therefore, the TDA decides to 
                        dispose of the data.
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Storage management information</em> (list of affected <em>AIPs</em>, <em>Files</em>)
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal request
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="1c">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Quality reports
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                    <cpp:supplier>CPP-019</cpp:supplier>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        The quality of the data no longer meets the minimum requirements of the 
                        designated community or the data is available in an alternative and higher quality
                        version or format. Therefore, the TDA decides to dispose of the data.
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Storage management information</em> (list of affected <em>AIPs</em>, <em>Files</em>)
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal request
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="1d">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Quality reports
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>                    
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Intellectual property change
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>                    
                    <cpp:supplier>CPP-020</cpp:supplier>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Risk detection
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>                    
                    <cpp:supplier>CPP-023</cpp:supplier>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        TDA gets a trigger event indicating that an <em>AIP</em> or <em>File</em> needs 
                        to be disposed of.
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Storage management information</em> (list of affected <em>AIPs</em>, <em>Files</em>)
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal request
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="1e">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Appraisal reports 
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        The retention period of the data has been fulfilled according to the
                        appraisal or reappraisal of the data.
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Storage management information</em> (list of affected <em>AIPs</em>, <em>Files</em>)
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            </cpp:stepGroup>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="2">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Storage management information</em> (list of affected <em>AIPs</em>, 
                            <em>Files</em>)
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal request
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            TDAs policy on disposal
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        Creation of a disposal plan for the data in question from the policy. It should 
                        address the following issues:
                    </span>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Creation of tombstone metadata for PIDs
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Defining the retention period between logical disposal and physical
                            disposal
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            Documenting the disposal request
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal plan
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="3">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal request
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        Document the disposal request (such as the reason), the affected
                        <em>AIPs</em> or <em>Files</em>, timestamps
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Provenance metadata</em>
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="4">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal plan
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Storage management information</em>
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        Implement deaccessioning/logical disposal. Prevent access to the
                        <em>Object</em>, its discovery, and exclude it from any external reporting
                        (such as statistical data generation).
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Provenance metadata</em>
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="5">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal plan
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        If identifiers exist: the creation of tombstone metadata.
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Tombstone metadata</em>
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="6">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal plan
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        Physical disposal of copies from primary random access media,
                        such as hard disk drives. Update <em>storage management information</em>
                        (removal of storage locations).
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Storage management information</em>
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Provenance metadata</em>
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="7">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal plan
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Storage management information</em>
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        Physical disposal of copies from secondary sequential access media, such as 
                        magnetic tapes and off-line copies. Usually done at later stages during (e.g.
                        Refreshment). Update <em>storage management information</em> (removal
                        of storage locations).
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Storage management information</em>
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            <em>Provenance metadata</em>
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            <cpp:step stepNumber="8">
                <cpp:input>
                    <cpp:inputElement>
                        <span>
                            Disposal is complete
                        </span>
                    </cpp:inputElement>
                </cpp:input>
                <cpp:stepDescription>
                    <span>
                        If evidence is required that disposal has been completed,
                        then create a certification of destruction that confirms that all
                        copies of the data have been permanently deleted.
                    </span>
                </cpp:stepDescription>
                <cpp:output>
                    <cpp:outputElement>
                        <span>
                            Destruction Certificate
                        </span>
                    </cpp:outputElement>
                </cpp:output>
            </cpp:step>
            </cpp:stepGroup>
        </cpp:stepByStepDescription>
    </cpp:process>
    <cpp:rationaleWorstCase>
        <cpp:purpose>
            <cpp:purposeDescription>
                <span>
                    Disposal could be legally mandatory in terms of privacy and retaining only
                    necessary content.
                 </span>
            </cpp:purposeDescription>
            <cpp:worstCase>
                <span>
                    Legal consequences
                </span>
            </cpp:worstCase>
        </cpp:purpose>
        <cpp:purpose>
            <cpp:purposeDescription>
                <span>
                    Not disposing of data in a timely way results in unnecessary and irrelevant
                    content being retained. This could worsen the consequences of cyber
                    attacks (e.g. ransomware of data that should have been disposed of before
                    the attack). Or if the data is compromised then it could result in
                    privacy breaches.
                 </span>
            </cpp:purposeDescription>
            <cpp:worstCase>
                <span>
                    Exploitation of security vulnerabilities, more costly to recover from cyber 
                    attacks, data privacy breaches
                </span>
            </cpp:worstCase>
        </cpp:purpose>
        <cpp:purpose>
            <cpp:purposeDescription>
                <span>
                    Retaining data that is no longer needed can impact on data quality
                    and integrity. Removing outdated, duplicated, or corrupted <em>Objects</em> helps
                    maintain the quality and usability of the TDA.
                 </span>
            </cpp:purposeDescription>
            <cpp:worstCase>
                <span>
                    Reduction in data quality and integrity
                </span>
            </cpp:worstCase>
        </cpp:purpose>
       <cpp:purpose>
            <cpp:purposeDescription>
                <span>
                    Removing data reduces the TDA’s storage and processing footprint.
                 </span>
            </cpp:purposeDescription>
            <cpp:worstCase>
                <span>
                    Increased costs data storage costs. Increased environmental footprint. Increased 
                    time and effort for future preservation activities (e.g. re-appraisal)
                </span>
            </cpp:worstCase>
        </cpp:purpose>
    </cpp:rationaleWorstCase>
    <cpp:cppRelationships>
        <cpp:relationship>
            <cpp:relationshipType>Requires</cpp:relationshipType>
            <cpp:relatedCPP>CPP-005</cpp:relatedCPP>
            <cpp:relationshipDescription>
                <span>
                    Identifiers must be taken care of during disposal
                </span>
            </cpp:relationshipDescription>
        </cpp:relationship>
        <cpp:relationship>
            <cpp:relationshipType>Requires</cpp:relationshipType>
            <cpp:relatedCPP>CPP-018</cpp:relatedCPP>
            <cpp:relationshipDescription>
                <span>
                    Soft dependency (i.e. may require): Community watch treats Disposal as a customer in 
                    cases where, for instance, a collection previously archived within the TDA has 
                    been also added to a different TDA and will be preserved there. Required actions 
                    downstream must be taken into account within the disposal process (e.g. notifying 
                    stakeholders about the changed preservation location).
                </span>
            </cpp:relationshipDescription>
        </cpp:relationship>
        <cpp:relationship>
            <cpp:relationshipType>Requires</cpp:relationshipType>
            <cpp:relatedCPP>CPP-025</cpp:relatedCPP>
            <cpp:relationshipDescription>
                <span>
                    Disposal prevents access to the <em>Objects</em>. Also, preventing access can be 
                    considered as "logical disposal"
                </span>
            </cpp:relationshipDescription>
        </cpp:relationship>
        <cpp:relationship>
            <cpp:relationshipType>Required by</cpp:relationshipType>
            <cpp:relatedCPP>CPP-016</cpp:relatedCPP>
            <cpp:relationshipDescription>
                <span>
                    A tombstone consisting of only Metadata - without the actual data -
                    has to be kept as a witness of the data’s former presence.
                </span>
            </cpp:relationshipDescription>
        </cpp:relationship>
        <cpp:relationship>
            <cpp:relationshipType>Not to be confused with</cpp:relationshipType>
            <cpp:relatedCPP>CPP-006</cpp:relatedCPP>
            <cpp:relationshipDescription>
                <span>
                    Disposal does not export the <em>Objects</em> from TDA.
                </span>
            </cpp:relationshipDescription>
        </cpp:relationship>
    </cpp:cppRelationships>





    <cpp:frameworkMappings>
        <cpp:mapping>
            <cpp:frameworkName>CoreTrustSeal</cpp:frameworkName>
            <cpp:correspondingTerm>
                <span>Deletion</span>
            </cpp:correspondingTerm>
            <cpp:correspondingSection>
                <span>
                    R14 The repository applies documented processes to ensure data and <em>Metadata</em>
                    storage and integrity.
                </span>
            </cpp:correspondingSection>
        </cpp:mapping>
        <cpp:mapping>
            <cpp:frameworkName>ISO 16363</cpp:frameworkName>
            <cpp:correspondingTerm>
                <span>Disposal</span>
                <span>Disposal records</span>
            </cpp:correspondingTerm>
            <cpp:correspondingSection>
                <span>3.3.3</span>
                <span>4.2.3.3</span>
            </cpp:correspondingSection>
        </cpp:mapping>
        <cpp:mapping>
            <cpp:frameworkName>OAIS</cpp:frameworkName>
            <cpp:correspondingTerm>
                <span>Deletion</span>
            </cpp:correspondingTerm>
            <cpp:correspondingSection>
                <span>3.3.6</span>
            </cpp:correspondingSection>
        </cpp:mapping>
        <cpp:mapping>
            <cpp:frameworkName>PREMIS</cpp:frameworkName>
            <cpp:correspondingTerm>
                <span>Deaccession </span>
            </cpp:correspondingTerm>
            <cpp:correspondingSection>
                <span>Glossary</span>
            </cpp:correspondingSection>
        </cpp:mapping>
    </cpp:frameworkMappings>
    <cpp:referenceImplementations>
        <cpp:publicDocumentation>
            <cpp:institution>
                <cpp:institutionLabel>TIB - Leibniz Information Centre for Science and Technology and University Library</cpp:institutionLabel>
                <cpp:institutionCountry>DE</cpp:institutionCountry>
                <cpp:institutionType>National library</cpp:institutionType>
                <cpp:institutionType>Non-commercial digital preservation service</cpp:institutionType>
                <cpp:institutionType>Research infrastructure</cpp:institutionType>
                <cpp:institutionType>Research performing organisation</cpp:institutionType>
            </cpp:institution>
            <cpp:linkToDocumentation xml:lang="en">
                <cpp:hyperlink>
                    https://knowledge.exlibrisgroup.com/Rosetta/Product_Documentation/Rosetta_Staff_Users_Guide/Data_Managers/005_Delete%2C_Restore%2C_Move%2C_and_Purge_IEs#About_Deleting.2C_Recovering.2C_and_Purging_an_IE
                </cpp:hyperlink>
            </cpp:linkToDocumentation>
        </cpp:publicDocumentation>        
        <cpp:publicDocumentation>
            <cpp:institution>
                <cpp:institutionLabel>Archivematica</cpp:institutionLabel>
                <cpp:institutionCountry>CA</cpp:institutionCountry>
                <cpp:institutionType>Digital preservation system</cpp:institutionType>
            </cpp:institution>
            <cpp:linkToDocumentation xml:lang="en">
                <cpp:hyperlink>
                    https://www.archivematica.org/en/docs/archivematica-1.17/user-manual/archival-storage/archival-storage/#delete-aip
                </cpp:hyperlink>
                <cpp:comment>
                    No explicit support for retention management, but there is a request/approve workflow 
                    for AIP deletion
                </cpp:comment>
            </cpp:linkToDocumentation>
        </cpp:publicDocumentation>
    </cpp:referenceImplementations>
</cpp:cpp>